Purim Sameach פורים שמח Purim Sameach everybody.
We're going to start.
Today's דף daf is י"א Yud Aleph and we are basically on
target. We start at the bottom of י"א עמוד ב', Yud Aleph
amud Beis, last line of י"א עמוד ב', Yud Aleph amud Beis,
and we are dealing now, we are moving on in the משנה.
Mishnah. So we've dealt with the issue of left hand and...
you don't need the key here.
Oh,
is that how you do it? Wow, it's power!
You just push the switch!
ונהפוך
הוא.
Venhapoich
hu.
Okay, so alright, so we're going on to the משנה. Mishnah. We
dealt with left hand and now we're dealing with the fact that
the קומץ kometz has to be whole, full, and if there's even
a tiny little pebble or a little piece of salt or a
little piece of the incense, frankincense in the לבונה, levona, it's פסול.
pasul. So let's take a look.
Last line of י"א עמוד ב'. Yud Aleph amud Beis. קמץ ועלה
בידו צרור, Kometz ve'ala beyado tzeror, so he did the קמיצה kmitza
and a little rock got in his hand,
או גרגיר מלח o gargir melach or a little like whatever kernel,
not kernel, whatever you call it of salt, crystal of salt, thank
you, או קורט של לבונה o kort shel levona
or also like a little whatever you would call a unit, crystal
of frankincense, it's פסול pasul because it is not full. So the
definition of full is obviously very precise. So the גמרא Gemara says
כולהי למה לי? Kulei lama li? Why did I need all three
examples? I mean they're pretty equivalent. דאי תנא צרור, De'i tana tzeror,
had it just said pebble, משום דלאו בר הקרבה הוא mishum delav
bar hakrava hu because that doesn't belong on the מזבח, mizbeach, so
that clearly would define it as a lacking or as a problem.
אבל מלח דבר הקרבה הוא, Aval melach debar hakrava hu, but salt,
since you put it on the מזבח mizbeach and after you actually
put the קומץ kometz on the מזבח mizbeach you add salt to
it because על כל קרבנך תקריב מלח, al kol korbanecha takriv melach,
so since it actually belongs there, אימא תתכשר, eima tiskasher, maybe it
will be כשר, kasher, meaning maybe even though it's not all pure
סולת soles and שמן, shemen,
this should be considered like an acceptable component of it. ואי תנא
מלח, Ve'i tana melach, and if it said salt, דלא איקבע בהדי
מנחה מעיקרא, delo ikva behadi mincha me'ikara, that was not designated originally
with the מנחה, mincha, you add the salt afterwards, מעיקרא, me'ikara, originally.
אבל לבונה דאיקבע בהדי מנחה מעיקרא, Aval levona de'ikva behadi mincha me'ikara,
but the frankincense which you put on the מנחה mincha when you
bring it, so maybe that's really one of the ingredients of the
מנחה mincha and that's not a problem of חסר, chaser, אימא תתכשר,
eima tiskasher, maybe it will be כשר, kasher, קמשמע לן. kamashma lan.
So
yes, any one of those would have told you that it has
to be full, but it wouldn't have told you that these items
are not necessarily considered to be a non-full handbreath because maybe, especially
the later ones, the salt and the לבונה levona might have been
considered to be an acceptable element of that handbreath. רש"י Rashi of
course says well then why not just start with לבונה? levona? He
doesn't really give an answer, but that's why anyway it's telling you
it's not just that even these things are not considered like you
have a full handbreath. Okay, and then we get to the next
sort of summary statement in the משנה, Mishnah, מפני שאמרו הקומץ החסר
או היתר פסול mipnei she'omru hakometz hachaser o hayaser pasul
because they said the קומץ kometz that is either lacking or surprisingly
even if there's more in your hand than the exact קומץ, kometz,
it's invalid.
So the גמרא Gemara says מאי איריא משום חסר ויתר תיפוק ליה
משום חציצה. Mai irya mishum chaser veyaser tipuk lei mishum chatzitza.
So the גמרא Gemara says why are you giving these examples of
lacking or being too much, why is it a חציצה chatzitza problem?
Now what's the חציצה chatzitza problem? So if it's lacking, you could
have lacking without the rock, you just don't have a full amount.
But it says if you do have the rock in it, so
then isn't that considered a חציצה? chatzitza? Now what's the חציצה chatzitza
problem? So רש"י Rashi says two possibilities: if it's at the between
your hand and the, like the rock is at the outer part
of the חציצה, chatzitza, so then it's getting between part of your
skin and touching the actual קומץ kometz itself. Let's say it's in
the inside. What?
Even so, so what? Because not every grain of the קומץ kometz
touches your skin.
Right, so presumably there we would say מין במינו אינו חוצץ. min
demino eino chotzeitz. So that's all considered one unit, it's not חוצץ.
chotzeitz. But there's still a connection, so there's not the most direct
connection perhaps to your skin but it goes around it. I mean
it's still just because that pebble
is
against your skin there's still no חציצה chatzitza between every part of
the handful flour and your hand.
Oh, I see what you're saying. That's interesting. I see what you're
saying. You're saying that if your fingers get it from above, then
it doesn't have to get from your palm below because it's all
considered... huh, that is an interesting question.
I'm feeling like פורים תורה Purim Torah
tonight.
Right, if you're wearing a glove then there's a חציצה. chatzitza.
Right, right, right.
That's a good question.
Unless part of the assumption is that the entire skin of your
hand, it's not just that there, the entire skin of your hand
has to be in contact with it and this is not. It's
even more complicated to explain what if the pebble's in the inside.
If the pebble's on the inside, רש"י Rashi says, well, that somewhat
divides it into two units. But again, that's really where Dov's question
is appropriate. What, I mean, if you had like a... plane that
was of pebbles, you could understand it's divided into units, but one
little point dividing it into units, I mean they're all connected in
every other point. So it's not exactly clear what is bothering the
גמרא Gemara here, and also why is יתר חציצה, yetar chatzitza, right?
If you have תרומה Terumah and let's say it's squirting out of
your between your fingers or something, where is that being a חציצה
chatzitza exactly? So anyway, let's see.
I mean you could say it's, it's out of the, well it's
not really a חציצה chatzitza problem, it's kind of out of the
קומץ. kometz.
Right, but then why does it פסול pasul the קומץ? kometz? קומץ,
kometz, why is it פסול? pasul?
Okay. So
it's
not exactly clear what this question is, but let's see what the
answer is.
So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבי ירמיה מן הצד. Amar Rabbi
Yirmeya min hatzad. It's at the edges, which רש"י Rashi says means
that, that it's like at the very top here, you know, and
the very bottom here. רש"י Rashi says it's at the edges because
after you take it, you wouldn't hold it, you know, you wouldn't
hold it like this because then stuff would fall down. רש"י Rashi
says you'd hold it like this to be so it would more
sort of wouldn't spill. Anyway, so it's at the edges right after
your pinky and right after your whatever this is, pointer finger. So
if you had a little rock there or a little rock here,
it would not, you know, get in between your skin. Of course
it doesn't explain why you wouldn't have the idea of the same
problem as the rock on the inside, you know, the חציצה chatzitza
between the two halves. So anyway, so that's where it is. It's
at the edges. אמר
ליה אביי לרבא כיצד קומץ? Amar lei Abaye le-Rava keitzad kometz? All
right, so it was not exactly clear what the question and the
answer was there but we'll move on. So אביי Abaye says to
רבא, Rava, how do you do קמיצה? kmitza? Finally, a practical question.
אמר ליה כדקמצי אינשי Amar lei ke-dekamtzi inshi like a normal person
would do קמיצה. kmitza. So whatever it is, you stick your hand
in and you scoop it up and nothing special.
Is that easy?
It's that easy, exactly, exactly.
So איתיבי, eitvei, but I'll ask you on this, זו זרת. zo
zeret. So this is a identifying of the fingers of your hand.
If you never learned the right the Hebrew words for the fingers
of your hand or their halakhic significance, here we go. The pinky
is the זרת, zeret, the next one, what do we call that,
the ring finger, is the קמיצה, kmitza, the middle one is the
אמה, amah, the pointer finger is the אצבע, etzba, זו אצבע, zo
etzba, זו גודל, zo godel, and the thumb is the גודל. godel.
Now why? Because when the תורה Torah says for example that the
what do you call it is a זרת, zeret, the חושן choshen
is a זרת ארכו, zeret arko, so זרת zeret is from the
edge of the thumb to the edge of the pinky, which is
really like oh, thank you.
Everybody is being so good here, oh my God, I was not,
I did not think I had like this. Okay, anyway, so right,
so anyway, from the edge of the thumb to the edge of
the pinky is a זרת zeret which is supposed to be to
about two טפחים. tfachim. So this is how you measure a זרת,
zeret, this is a קמיצה kmitza because it is, the קמיצה kmitza
is not with all five fingers, it's with three fingers. The bottom
of the what you say זרת? zeret? זרת, zeret, very funny. Okay,
so right, so that's, that's the קמיצה. kmitza. This is the אמה
amah because when you measure an אמה amah it's from your you
know the bottom of your elbow to the top of your middle
finger, that's an אמה. amah. This is an אצבע etzba for all
the things that require an אצבע etzba when the כהן Kohen puts
the placing on the חטאת Chatat and on the ear of the
מצורע, Metzora, and this is a גודל godel because when the כהן
Kohen puts it on the מצורע Metzora he puts it on the
גודל, godel, on the thumb.
So now we have the five halakhic fingers here. Okay, so what
we find out is is that this is the קמיצה kmitza and
presumably כדקמצי אינשי ke-dekamtzi inshi means with all your fingers. So he
says you can't tell me it means with all your fingers. So
let's take a look.
Okay,
so גמרא Gemara says אלא להשוות. ela le-hashvot. So he did not
mean that that you take all, you take it with all five
fingers and you leave it that way. I mean it's a question
how exactly to explain this because of the next line of the
גמרא, Gemara, but some think it means yes you start by taking
it like people take with all five fingers but then you use
your thumb and your pinky to rub away the extra, so in
the end he agrees you're left with three, which is this makes
this a קמיצה, kmitza, but you use your thumb and your pinky
to get rid of anything that is coming out beyond.
Okay,
let's take a look. So
yeah. Now רש"י Rashi reads it slightly differently, that's the way that's
the way the parentheses read it. If you look at the parentheses,
whoever was that, כלומר קומץ מלא היד, klomar kometz melo hayad, you
take your full hand, כדי שלא יהא חסר, kedei shelo yehei chaseir,
that making sure you don't have too little, ואחר כך מוחק באצבע
קטנה מלמטה, ve-acharkach mocheik be-etzba ktana milmata, then you do it. Now
the problem with that is it makes a lot of sense but
the next גמרא Gemara is going to say that you use only
that you use only three fingers to do the act. So רש"י
Rashi says what he says when he said כדקמצי אינשי, ke-dekamtzi inshi,
that what רבי Rebbe was saying is I did mean to say
you grab it with all five fingers but I mean you use
all five fingers. After doing this, you use
היכי עביד, Heychei avid, how do
you exactly do it? אמר רב זוטרא בר טוביה אמר רב. Amar
Rav Zutra bar Tuvya amar Rav. So רב זוטרא בר טוביה Rav
Zutra bar Tuvya says in the name of רב, Rav, חופה שלוש
אצבעותיו עד שמגיע על פס ידו. chofeh shalosh etzba’otav ad shemagia al
pas yado. You bend over your three fingers, so notice you're doing
the act really not with all five fingers, which is why רש"י
Rashi says what he does
that רבא Rava would not disagree with it. You bend over your
three middle fingers until you get to like the palm of your
hand, וקומץ, ve'komatz, and then you take the קמיצה. kemitza. So you
basically do the act with three fingers and not with these two.
You use these two maybe to smooth it over, but you actually
do the scooping with three fingers. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
we taught similarly. מלא קומצו. Melo kumtzo. So the תורה Torah says
you shall take the fullness of your handbreadth. יכול מבורץ? Yachol mevoratz?
Perhaps it means that it should be like, you know, sprouting over,
it should be you know, overflowing. תלמוד לומר בקומצו, Talmud lomar be'kumtzo,
with his handbreadth means exactly the size of a handbreadth. אי בקומצו,
Ee be'kumtzo, if it means with, יכול בראשי אצבעותיו? yachol berosh etzba’otav?
Maybe it doesn't mean full, maybe it means like just using, you
know, your fingertips to collect something. תלמוד לומר מלא קומצו. Talmud lomar
melo kumtzo. It has to be full, full but not overfull. הא
כיצד? Ha keitzad? How do you do it? חופה שלוש אצבעותיו על
פס ידו. chofeh shalosh etzba’otav al pas yado. You bend over the
three fingers, the full three fingers onto the palm of your hand,
וקומץ, ve'komatz, and you do the קמיצה. kemitza. Okay, so that's like
we said before, you use three fingers and presumably the thumb and
the pinky is just for smoothing. Now, במחבת ובמרחשת, bemachvat u’vemarcheshet, what
do you do about the מנחות minchas that are not, that are
baked, that are hard? Right, that's good if it's all flour and
oil. What if you do if they're hard? So what the תורה
Torah says is פתות אותה פתיתים, patot osah p'titim, right? That you
break it up into little pieces, crumbs, I mean not tiny crumbs
but whatever, pieces. Right, you
fold it over and then quarters and eighths and whatever, right? We'll
talk about that. Anyway, and then you do it. So there are
little chunks that you're doing. But still, it's a little bit harder
because you're not going to get an exact קומץ, komatz, right? Stuff
will be sticking out if they're crumbs. So let's see what you
do.
במחבת ובמרחשת, bemachvat u’vemarcheshet, מוחק באגודלו מלמעלה ובאצבע קטנה מלמטה. mochek begudlo
milma'alah u've'etzba ktanah milmata. You use your thumb above and your pinky
below to smooth it over. So here actually it only talks about
the smoothing when it gets to the, the ones that are baked.
Presumably if you just did the simple flour and oil you could
do it exactly, you wouldn't even need to smooth, but if you
have chunks, then you're going to need to smooth with your thumb
and pinky. וזו היא עבודה קשה שבמקדש. Ve’zu hi avodah kashah she’be’mikdash.
This is the hardest עבודה avodah in the מקדש. Mikdash. It's pretty
funny of all of the things that they did, this does not
sound so difficult. But somehow I guess the point
is, how many fingers do you have?
Pinky to like break, right, and I guess the point is to
get it exactly, not any, not a little bit less, not a
little bit more, right? יתר וחסר פסול, Yeter ve’chaser pasul, so to
get exactly the right amount.
Still can't get my head around מליקה. melikah.
What? Still can't get your head around מליקה. melikah. So that's what
the גמרא's Gemara going to say. What? This is the most difficult?
We have a couple of other things that we've identified as the
most difficult.
What are the most difficult?
I'll bet you, that's exactly what it's going to say. Okay, so
the גמרא Gemara says: זו היא?
זו ותו לא Zo hi? Zu ve’tu lo? This and no other
is difficult? ואיכא מליקה ואיכא חפינה? Ve’ika melikah ve’ika chafinah? Don't we
have מליקה melikah and חפינה chafinah which also we use this phrase
זו היא עבודה קשה? zo hi avodah kashah? Now what מליקה melikah
we know is שחיטה shechting the bird from behind with the כהן's
kohen fingernail. חפינה chafinah is on יום כיפור Yom Kippur where it
says מלא חופניו. melo chofnav. It says חופן chofen is also like
your, a handful, but it's plural so it's two. So he takes
the fullness of his, you know, handbreadths and he puts them in
like this, he scoops it up like that and he puts it
in a כלי. kli. So what's the big deal about that?
No, don't they mean that, because you have to dexterity, right, to
turn it around?
Yes, exactly. That's what it means. Because when he gets to the
קודש קדשים, Kodesh Kadashim, okay, he's got the, he's got it in
his arm, he's holding this thing in his arm and he's got
to and he's got to sort of, you know, move it over
to get it close enough to manipulate with his elbow and then
when he gets it close he's got to turn it into one
handbreadth and then into the other and somehow get the two handbreadths
in without using his hands actually to manipulate. He's basically doing it
with his elbow. Or put it on a גודא דפני.
guda d’afni. What? Exactly, to put it in some place on a...
right, exactly. So the גמרא Gemara says: אלא זו
היא אחת מעבודות קשות שבמקדש. Ela zo hi achat me’avodot kashot she’be’mikdash.
It is one of the hardest. Actually of all of them, it
seems the easiest but okay. אמר רב פפא: Amar Rav Pappa: פשיטא
לי מלא קומצו כדי קמצי אינשי. Pshita li melo kumtzo k’dekomtzi inchi.
Again that phrase which we were not happy with before, but I
get that when you take the קומץ komitz it's like people do
it, meaning maybe only use three fingers, but it's obvious what you
do, you stick your hand in and you scoop it up. Okay,
so you only take three fingers. That I get. Now, בעא רב
פפא: ba’ei Rav Pappa: Here's my question. קמץ בראשי אצבעותיו מה? Komatz
berosh etzba’otav mah? Let's say you don't do it the normal way.
You get the full amount in your hand, but you don't do
it the normal way. You just use your finger, you know, you
slowly with your the tips of your finger do it. Eventually you
get, you scoop enough in, but you don't do a real like
grab, okay? So let's say you only use ראשי אצבעותיו. roshei etzbaosav.
מהו? mahu? מן הצדדים? min hatzdadim? Let's say you do it from
the side. What does the side mean? So maybe it means you
scoop it up like this, okay, with one explanation, or רש״י Rashi
says maybe you've got your thing, you know, you make a hole
here, like you make like a tube in your hand and you
scoop it up like that. All right? You do something like that.
That's מן הצדדים מהו. min hatzdadim mahu. חופן בזה. chofen bezeh. Oh,
my, did I skip a line?
Yeah. ממטה למעלה. mimata lemala.
Oh, thank you. ורש״י מהו מן הצדדין מהי ממטה למעלה
מאי? verashi mahu min hatzdadin mahi mimata lemala mai? From below to
above what?
I forget what, how רש״י Rashi explains that. Hold on. ממטה למעלה?
mimata lemala? שהכניס אצבעותיו דקמח וגב היד כנגד. shehichnis etzbeosav dekemach vegav
hayad keneged.
Right.
So you basically you go like this. You stick your hand in
like that and you scoop it up like that rather than scoop
it like that. Okay.
Wait, so you're supposed to go like something like like you're supposed
to put it like, you know, like a karate chop sort of?
And then what? How's it actually supposed to go, the whole?
Like this. Yeah,
but
do you just go like this, or are you supposed to put
your hand like, you know?
No, the hand on top like this, the hand enters. Well, that's
what, see? The normal way you קמיצה kmitza is you put your
the palm of your hand on the מנחה mincha and you scoop
into it. So now we're asking: what if you do it like
this? What if you do it like this? Okay, all those alternatives,
does it matter? As long as you wind up with the right
amount in your hand. תיקו. teiku. So it leaves this as an
unanswered question. Okay, so
אמר רב פפא. amar Rav Pappa. Now we're going to move from
קומץ kometz to חפינה. chafina. פשיטא לי מלוא חופניו כדחפני אינשי. pshita
li milo chofnav kichofnei inshi. When you say the fill of your
hand, it's like normal people, if I were to tell you fill
your two hands, you'd scoop it up, right? So you would go
like this, right? Isn't that how you normally scoop something into your
two hands? So that's obvious that that works. So
what about בעי רב פפא? ba'ei Rav Pappa? חופן בראשי אצבעותיו מהו?
chofen beroshei etzbaosav mahu? Let's say again, you only use your fingertips,
but you got it filled. מן הצדדים מהו? min hatzdadim mahu? From
the sides. Now what do sides mean? This is the sides. So
רש״י Rashi says here's where רש״י Rashi says sides could mean like
you scoop it in like this, like sort of, you know, with
your hand like that rather than like that. Okay. חופן בזו ובזו
וקירבן זו אצל זו מהו? chofen bezo uvezo vekirvan zo etzel zo
mahu? You did each hand, you filled up separately, and then you
brought them together to be a double handful. Is that good? מהו?
mahu? זו אצל זו מהו? zo etzel zo mahu? תיקו. teiku.
So we don't know the answer. בעי רב פפא. ba'ei Rav Pappa.
דווקא? davka? What?
Is it a question about about the the amount that's in there
or about the technique?
No, the whole point is, and this is like, you know, a
major theme we've discussed before about the focus sort of on the
object if you would, or the result as opposed to the process.
Here he's assuming that you're going to get the right amount, but
the question is: does the process matter? We normally talk about this
and this and this. Is that just to ensure the right amount,
or is there a specific הלכה halacha of an act of קמיצה
kmitza that has to be done in a very narrowly defined way?
That's essentially what he's asking.
Why you have to do it with the
body?
That's an interesting question, but the תורה Torah says, I mean I
can't, you know,
it involves all these other things, the כלי. kli.
I know, but when they do the מליקה, melika, for example, right,
they break the neck of the bird, they do it with his
fingernail, with his hand.
Okay, but but as you know the flour is, you know, it
gets hands dirty.
Oh, yeah.
It's a good question, but you know maybe the תורה Torah is
also saying that it depends on each כהן, kohen, the amount is
defined separately, you know, based on his own handbreadth. But that's not
really a sufficient answer because you could make a כלי kli based
on my handbreadth and I could use it. It's just the way
the תורה Torah says it. You know, in a way that's similar
to what's being asked here: what do I care about the process,
or do I care that it gets done?
But at least in terms of using the actual body of the
כהן, kohen, that seems to be that we do care about the
about that component.
You answered my question well before because at some point we care
that, you know, you actually do the קמיצה, kmitza, you go like
this, right? Let's say, you know, they care at all how you
got your hand in there? Let's say it went like this and
then turned it around. Does that matter?
Oh, I see, I see.
So that that didn't
come up in רב פפא׳ס Rav Pappa's question. Presumably that's, right, presumably
that's prior to the actual act
itself, so we don't really care about that at all. Or even
after once I'm done, I can go like this and it's like
no one cares about that either.
Right, presumably yes.
And I see answer to these תיקו, teiku, in other words, do
they just not know the tradition?
Yeah, I mean, first of all, what's clear is they almost have
no tradition by קדשים. kodashim. I mean, it's very rare that they
quote actual.
But is it just that they have some but not others?
So they, I wouldn't say as much that they don't have tradition
as much as that they don't have,
you know, any any recorded opinions on this matter. They don't have
any texts to work off. Meaning all of the texts they're working
off of, how many of them actually say this is what I
saw in the בית המקדש, beis hamikdash, right? It's all speculation or
interpretation based on, you know, פסוקים pesukim and based on, if you
would, hermeneutic traditions or but not on, you know, traditions of actually
having observed. So here the basic point is there's no text. If
there's no text, you know, what do you have to go on?
The כהן׳ס kohen's name is חפני. Chofni.
Well, that could very well be true. I don't know if I
was suggesting that, but that could be. Now, what's his name
suggested—although afterward scholars sort of thought that was ridiculous—but I'm trying to
remember who it was. No, no, no, not Milgram.
Who's the guy that did the ספרא? Sifra? The academic version of
the ספרא Sifra from JTS?
I don't know, one of the earlier JTS scholars. Anyway, he thought—it's
pretty well assumed that the ספרא Sifra is one of the earliest
מדרשי הלכה. Midrashei Halakha. Now, the reason obviously could be because, you
know, that's something that you do every single day, and obviously the
כהנים, Kohanim, you know, at an earlier stage probably were the ones
that were also, you know, יורו משפטיך ליעקב, Yoru mishpatecha le-Yaakov, they
were the ones—the split between כהנים Kohanim and the rabbinic class at
an earlier stage, and you know, obviously they want, you know, their—it's
stuff that they need to really know in every tiny little detail.
But whoever this was—and I can't believe I'm forgetting the name—anyway,
Finkelstein, maybe it was Finkelstein, I think it was Finkelstein suggested that
this was actually like the first written תורה, Torah, you know, the
first written תורה שבעל פה. Torah she-be-al peh. That they wrote this
down and that this was like a handbook for the כהנים. Kohanim.
So it wasn't just like the
earliest sort of book in terms of an oral book—they had plenty
of oral books—but you know, we talked about how they published in
an oral culture, but that there was actually a written book and
it served as the written handbook for the כהנים. Kohanim. I don't
know, I mean afterwards scholars have really, you know, very strongly rejected
that, but why did I mention any of that? Because your question
was—oh, about where—about the tradition. So yeah, that is an interesting sort
of ironic point, is that on the one hand in terms of
the מדרשי הלכה, Midrashei Halakha, we seem to have some of the
earliest traditions in ויקרא, Vayikra, but in terms of actual hard facts
of what they do, we don't, we seem to have barely anything.
It was Finkelstein who made this—who did the ספרא Sifra or had
this exact specific thesis? ספרא. Sifra. The ספרא. Sifra. So I think
he was the one with this thesis as well. What did you
do, you Wikipedied it? ספרא Sifra JTS.
Yeah. What happened with the left flour—for what—what happened with the leftover
from it?
Then the כהנים Kohanim would eat it. The leftover flour of the
מנחה Mincha would be eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim.
Yeah, you scoop it up, you burn that, and what's left over
is eaten by the כהנים. Kohanim. It's like the meat that's left
over from the קרבנות. Korbanot. Okay? All right, so that's the question
about
חפינה. Chafina. בעי רב פפא, Ba-ei Rav Pappa, Rav Pappa asked. דבקה
לקומץ. Davke le-komitz. Now this is like, you know, this is probably
never a practical question, but this is really like just trying to
be like creative. So you stuck the קומץ Kometz בדפני דמנא. be-dafnei
de-mana. You didn't actually put it at the base of the vessel.
It was sticky because it had oil, so you made a little
ball out of it or whatever you did and you smacked it
against the side, the walls of the vessel. So it was in
the vessel but it wasn't sitting on the floor.
Meaning you put it in a new one, right?
No, no, no, yeah, you took—yeah, you took it out of this,
and when you put it in the כלי שרת, Kli Sharet, rather
than just letting it drop,
you—you know—smacked it on the side and it stuck to the wall
without actually hitting the bottom. Okay?
Could that be a problem?
Well, let's see. מאי? Mai? What's the law? תוך כלי בעינן ואיכא.
Toch kli ba-inan ve-ika. In the vessel, is that what we need?
And it's in the vessel. או דילמא, O dilma, or maybe the
עבודה Avoda of placing it in the vessel is הנחה בתוכו בעינן.
hanacha be-tocho ba-inan. Why? Well, because again, I believe these questions are
on the one hand the result and on the other hand the
process. It could be that קידוש כלי Kiddush Kli works if it's
anywhere in the vessel, it doesn't have to be at the floor
of the vessel. Didn't we have that before? Yeah, but right, it
certainly doesn't work if it's out of the vessel. But here it's
in. That may be sufficient. But if there's an act of נתינה
בכלי, Netina ba-kli, נתינה Netina might mean, you know, normal נתינה. Netina.
The normal way you put something in a כלי Kli is you
drop it and you let it fall, you don't just let it
hang, it's suspended in a כלי. Kli. So one way of understanding
this is not the question of how כלי שרת Kli Sharet operates
but the act of נתינה בכלי Netina ba-kli of the קומץ, Kometz,
of קידוש כלי. Kiddush Kli. Okay, so that's one question. תיקו, Teiku,
we don't know the answer. בעי מר בר רב אשי. Ba-ei Mar
bar Rav Ashi. So now once Rav Pappa—oh, he's going with this.
Oh, yeah. Now once Rav Pappa opened the door, מר בר רב
אשי Mar bar Rav Ashi is going to ask the following.
הפכיה למנא ודבקה לקומץ בארעא דמנא מאי. Hafkhei le-mana ve-davkei le-komitz be-ara
de-mana mai. You turned the כלי Kli upside down and you stuck
it on the floor. Now רש"י Rashi explains this to mean that
it was like a vessel that had a little lip at the
bottom, you know, after the base there was still—the lip extended. So
even when you turned it upside down, you had walls and a
floor even—you know—even on the other side. Really?
And then it just stays sticky and it sticks.
That's what I thought. I thought the simple explanation is you stuck
it on the floor but the כלי Kli was upside down, right?
So it's totally in and it's on the floor but the floor
is now the ceiling. So that's what I thought the גמרא Gemara
said. Let's see the way it frames the question. מאי? Mai? הנחה
בתוכו בעינן ואיכא. Hanacha be-tocho ba-inan ve-ika. Do you need it to
be placed inside and it is? So you could see either רש"י's
Rashi way or my way. works in the sense of being placed
inside. או דלמא כתיקונו בעינן וליכא? O dilma kitikuno be'inan ve'leika? The
normal way? And you don't have it. תיקו. Teyku. So he says
we don't know. So the problem with רש"י's Rashi approach is that
normally we say that כלי שרת Klei sharet are only מקדש, mekadesh,
you know, in the normal way in like they're used. That if
you put something, if you use it in this way, if you
would use the upside down part it would not create קידוש כלי
שרת. Kiddush klei sharet. So I really have a hard problem, you
know, understanding רש"י Rashi because normally we say כלי שרת klei sharet
don't function that way. They function דרך תשמישו. derech tashmisho. So the
other way is I think more interesting. It is on the inside,
it is on the floor, except it's being suspended by the floor
because you're holding the כלי kli upside down. Anyway the גמרא Gemara
does not answer this question. Well, that's a question. I'm not sure
it's asking about קידוש כלי שרת. Kiddush klei sharet. It's assuming perhaps
that קדושת כלי kedushat kli would function in these cases. It's asking
whether this is a הנחה בכלי, hanacha bakli, you know, and I
think that that is again like the theme going on here. There's
two things going on, the קידוש kiddush of the כלי kli and
the act and the ritual of the כהן kohen that's doing. That's
how I understand the question. Not is it—not is כלי שרת מקדש
klei sharet mekadesh this way, but is this an acceptable הנחה? hanacha?
The same way we're asking is it an acceptable קומץ? kometz? Is
it an acceptable חפינה? chafina? If you do the process differently.
So it's still מקודש mekudash but just may not work—so you're suggesting
it's מקודש mekudash but the מנחה mincha may be פסולה psula because
it's not a good הנחה. hanacha. Right. So basically you have to
burn it because it's מקודש. mekudash.
Yes, although on last כלי kli you get to the question about
אין כלי שרת מקדשין אלא מדעת ein klei sharet mekadeshin ela mida'at
and therefore if it wasn't going to work, you know, you tried
to make it dependent, but at least in theoretically yes.
Another question. What about like the פסוק הקריבהו נא לפחתך, pasuk hakrivehu
na le'fachatecha, right? In other words, the whole thing should just not
work because you're not doing it in a nice honorable way?
Well, you're way before you're actually bringing it. You're not redefining the
object. The object is not inappropriate. But what you—the—I think the quote
you want to say is אין דרך שירות
בכך.
ein derech
sheirut bekach. It's not למה לשרת. lama lesharet. So sometimes we exclude
acts from considering like עבודה avoda because it's not דרך שירות. derech
sheirut. Right. Okay. So I don't know. Are these things so offensive
that they're not דרך שירות? derech sheirut? You stick it on a
side rather than let it fall to the bottom?
It's not necessarily a matter of offense, it's just not what's done,
you know? It's not דרך שירות. derech sheirut.
Right, so I think that's what רב פפא Rav Pappa is asking.
When you say "what's done," what's your degree of tolerance
of things that are not the norm? You know, one—that's another way
to frame the question. Meaning, one way to frame the question is
a fundamental question. Do I even care how it's done or do
I just care that it gets there? The other way to frame
it is, of course I care how it's done, but how much
off of the norm is considered unacceptable? Like maybe one degree of
what do you call it? What's that called? Deviation, right. One standard
deviation, not two standard deviations. So there's a lot of ways of
understanding it.
Upside down, I mean, no one's really doing that.
I understand. Okay.
So you think this—this would really be a problem of דרך שירות?
derech sheirut? I think that would be...
All right, that is a good point. Let's take a look now
at the משנה. Mishnah. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? Now the
funny thing is that this line, you know, sometimes it's the editor
as we saw in the last פרק perek of זבחים Zevachim that
decides where to break up the משניות. Mishnayot. Given the discussion we
just had in the גמרא, Gemara, the editor should have put this
line of the משנה Mishnah in the previous one or the גמרא
Gemara we just had after this because you'll see, this is exactly
the discussion we had. כיצד הוא עושה? Keitzad hu oseh? How do
you do the קמיצה? kmitza? פושט את אצבעותיו על פס ידו. Poshet
et etzbe'otav al pas yado. So you, you know,
you fold over your finger onto your palm. So that's exactly the
discussion we just had. So it does not belong here. Anyway, ריבה
שמנה חסר שמנה Riba shamna chaser shamna or חיסר לבונה פסולה. chisar
levona psula. If you have too much oil—before we were talking about
you didn't have—you had too much of the flour in your hand,
or not the flour, too much of the מנחה mincha in your
hand or too little in your hand. Now we're talking about the
ingredients in making the מנחה. mincha. You added too much oil. You
didn't have enough oil. You're supposed to have a לוג log of
oil. So that would invalidate it. Or חיסר לבונה פסולה, chisar levona
psula, if you didn't have all of the לבונה, levona, it is
פסול. pasul. But we're going to see in a minute there's a
major debate of how much לבונה levona you really need at the
end of the day.
What about water? Don't some of them need water? What? Don't some
of them need water ever?
No. Where does it say water ever?
No, I mean like, aren't some of those like you need to
boil them? חלוטה ברותחין. chaluta berotchin. So they don't care about how
much water you...
Oh.
No. Oh. That's funny.
I thought some of them needed some water, no?
Well, think so.
I have to get my מנחה mincha book.
I don't think you use water in them. No. Oil and flour.
Okay. I don't think so.
מנחת מאפה תנור Minchat ma'afeh tanur then, how is it baked? No
water?
Well, you use oil. I mean, oil is—I don't know. Will oil
and flour—can it cause something to—I mean, oil has a lot of
liquid. What?
Donuts.
Donuts don't have any water added to the flour?
They have to have water.
They must have water.
Actually, I don't know.
Sugar.
All right.
Okay. There's no water in it.
Oh, that's a good point.
Oil, sugar... oh, cookies.
Okay. All right. Okay. היכי דמי? Heichi dami? Okay. How is this—how
do you—what's the case where if you have too much oil it's
invalid? ריבה שמנה, Riba shamna, היכי דמי ריבה שמנה? heichi dami riba
shamna? What does it mean too much oil? case of too much
oil, אמר רבי אלעזר *Amar Rabbi Elazar* כגון שהפריש שני לוגין *kegon
shehifrish shenai login*.
So actually it means that you even designated for the מנחה Mincha.
*mincha*, you were sanctified. Here is my עישרון סולת *isaron solet* and
here is two לוג Log, *log* of oil. I really like oil,
I'm going to put two לוג log *log* and you sanctified it
for the מנחה Mincha. *mincha*. So it really means you made the
מנחה mincha, *mincha*, you were מקדיש *makdish* it, that it should have
extra oil. You didn't just throw in some extra oil, you sanctified
the extra oil. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, וליוקמה *v'lokma*,
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* assumes that that means that in another circumstance
would not be a problem if it was just random extra oil
added in. וליוקמה כגון דעריב בה שמן דחולין *v'lokma kegon d'arvei shemen
d'chulin*, why not just say that you added oil that was not
sanctified ושמן דחברתה *v'shemen d'chaverta* or oil from a different מנחה mincha.
*mincha*? Meaning, why did you only give the example that you added
oil that you sanctified oil for this מנחה mincha, *mincha*? וכי תימא
שמן דחולין ושמן דחברתה לא פסל *v'chi teima shemen d'chulin v'shemen d'chaverta
lo pasal*, let's say you say that it would not invalidate because
meaning, here's an interesting point, meaning when you say too much oil
is no good, is that mean that you've redefined it so it
has different proportions which maybe is only when you sanctify more oil
for it? Now I've said I am making this with a different
proportion of flour to oil, or is it even if in practice
there's too much oil? So maybe that's what maybe he would think
that if other oil came in and you did not sanctify it
for it, maybe it wouldn't be a problem.
So we're talking about the right amount of oil but just from
a different source?
Because it sounds like... yes. No, not the right amount, the wrong
amount of oil. I have here my עישרון *isaron* of סולת *solet*
and I get one לוג log *log* of שמן *shemen*, okay? And
he said, רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said, what does it mean too
much oil? I said, I'm sanctifying two לוגין *login* of שמן *shemen*
for it.
So you didn't actually mix it in?
No, no, and then you mixed it in. That's... and then you
mixed... yeah right, that's where we're assuming and then you went and
mixed it in. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is saying, well why
did you have to say that? Why didn't you just say that
you mixed in extra oil? Right. So it sounds like maybe he's
saying that if there's accidentally too much oil it's not a problem.
There has to be intentionally too much oil, it has to be
defined as the oil of the מנחה mincha, *mincha*. But if you
really say that, can you really say that? But then, and now
people take out like the next six words because the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara*'s normal phrase is וכי תימא *v'chi teima*, right? What's the normal
way? If you say X, אלא מעתה *ela me'ata*, then what would
you say about the following case? So מתקיף לה *matkif la*, you
know, so and so asked the following question never appears after וכי
תימא *v'chi teima*, right? The way the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* operates, it's:
if you say this, then רב פפא *Rav Pappa* asked the following
question. Right? That's not the normal way the sentence is structured. So
anyway, we'll skip those five words, but you really see, I mean
my God, look at all these parentheses, you know, and after you
really see that the text is not as, you know, well-edited as
it is in other מסכתות *masechtot*. וכי תימא שמן דחולין ושמן דחברתה
לא פסל *v'chi teima shemen d'chulin v'shemen d'chaverta lo pasal*, if you
say other oil would not invalidate, אלא מעתה *ela me'ata*, so skipping
about five words, if that's true, מנחת חוטא דפסיל בה שמן *minchat
choteh d'pasil bah shemen*. So the תורה Torah *Torah* says by the
מנחה mincha. *mincha* of a מנחת חוטא *minchat choteh*, it says לא
ישים עליה שמן ולא יתן עליה לבונה Levonah *lo yasim aleha shemen
v'lo yiten aleha levonah*. Okay, כי מנחת קנאות היא *ki minchat kenaot
hi*, at least by the סוטה *Sotah*. Don't put on it oil.
So what type of oil would invalidate? If we're saying any oil
that was not sanctified for it would not be considered problematic oil,
then how could you invalidate a מנחה mincha? *mincha* of a חוטא
*choteh*? Why not? אי דידיה *ei dideh*, if he sanctified oil to
go with this מנחת חוטא *minchat choteh*, לית ליה *leit leh*, לית
לה *leit lah*. The תורה Torah. *Torah* never says any oil goes
with the מנחת חוטא *minchat choteh*, so the קדושה *kedusha* would be
meaningless. If the תורה Torah *Torah* says one לוג *log* and you
sanctify two לוגין *login*, at least the קדושה *kedusha* is a meaningful
statement. But here the קדושה *kedusha* of oil for the מנחת חוטא
*minchat choteh* is meaningless. So any oil you add is going to
be considered extraneous oil. אי דחולין ודחברתה *ei d'chulin v'd'chaverta*, so if
it's non-sanctified or if it's from another מנחה mincha, *mincha*, הא אמרת
לא פסיל *ha amrat lo pasil*, you say it's not valid, it's
not... does not invalidate. So רב פפא *Rav Pappa*'s statement that you
need to sanctify, or no, he said you did sanctify, we read
it to mean you need to sanctify, so there's a certain logic
to it. It's not a problem if it happens to be too
much oil, it's only a problem if you've redefined it, you've sanctified
extra oil for it. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, you won't
have a case then by a מנחת חוטא *minchat choteh*. Any oil
you add to a מנחת חוטא *minchat choteh* is always fundamentally external
to the מנחה mincha *mincha*. And therefore you would never have an
invalidity. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says, רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar*, so
you're right. Let's re-read, let's re-understand רב אלעזר *Rav Elazar*. רב אלעזר
לא מבעיא קאמר *Rav Elazar lo mibaya ka'amar*, goes without saying. לא
מבעיא דחולין ודחברתה דפסיל *lo mibaya d'chulin v'd'chaverta d'pasil*. No, no, he
didn't mean only if you sanctify. Obviously if it's oil that doesn't
belong there, it's non-sanctified oil or it is oil from another מנחה
mincha *mincha*, it has no place to be part of this מנחה
mincha. *mincha*, that would invalidate it. אבל הפריש לו שני לוגין *aval
hifrish lo shenai login*, but if I sanctify two לוג *log*, הואיל
והאי חזי ליה והאי חזי ליה *hoil v'hai chazi leh v'hai chazi
leh*, I could use either לוג *log*, אימא לא ליפסול *eima lo
lipsol*, maybe if I use both it's not פסול pasul? *pasul* because
they're not inappropriate. I mean it's too much, but it's not inappropriate,
קא משמע לן Ka mashma lan *ka mashma lan*. So it teaches
you yes. So when רב פפא *Rav Pappa* said if you sanctify,
it means even if you sanctify. Okay, clearly we're going the opposite
way. Extraneous oil clearly doesn't belong and invalidates. If I sanctify, maybe
because I could use either that they each have, you know, are
fit. to be part of the mixture.
But then I put in both.
And then I put in both, but I still might think it’s
not like something’s here that fundamentally doesn’t belong. No, it’s פסול pasul?
because it’s too much. So what do you even if it’s fundamentally
belongs. What do you ופדית Uf’dita and you use the money towards
another מנחה. mincha. Okay. ומנא ליה לרבי אלעזר הא? U’mina leh l’Rabbi
Elazar ha? Now that we’re saying this, where does he know this?
What does he know? Even if you sanctify. אמר רבא, Amar Rava,
or what מתניתין קשיא ליה? Matnisin kashya leh? The language of the
משנה Mishna bothered him. מאי איריא דתני ריבה שמנה? Mai irya detani
riba shemanah? That if you had too much of its oil. ליתני
ריבה השמן. Lisney riba hashemen. Let the משנה Mishna say if you
put in too much oil. So too much of its oil means
it was oil that actually was connected to it. אלא הא קא
משמע לן דאף אגב דהפריש שני לוגין, Ela ha ka mashma lan
de’af agav dehifrish shney login, even if you sanctify two לוג, it
is invalid even though it is its oil. If it’s too much,
it’s a problem. Okay, so good. So now we know you need
the right proportion. Right amount of flour, right amount of oil. Different
proportions no good. If you take too much or take too little,
no good. As again, it’s quite fascinating because to think about how
precise this has to be as opposed to the animal sacrifices. Animal,
what do you do? You slaughter it, you catch some of the
blood, you’re done. So again, it has to do with the fact,
I think as we pointed out before, that this is being manufactured.
And since it’s being manufactured, it has to be done exactly correctly
and it’s harder to get to to say that you have the
exact item here. Maybe also it’s a corresponding to the fact that
there’s no problem of מום. Mum. So at some logical level, the
correspondence of מום Mum are these physical problems with it that correspond
to the concept of מום Mum by the animals. Okay.
חסר לבונה. Chisar levonah. If you have too much of it, of
it frankincense. Now, here’s let me just tell you what we’re going
to see and then we’ll see it because it’s a little.
Too much too little.
Too little. Did I say too much? Too little. I’m sorry. The
גמרא Gemara is going to actually ask why it didn’t say too
much. We’ll get to that in a minute. Anyway, here’s the point.
The תורה says that you put the לבונה Levonah on it, but
it doesn’t say how much.
So the חז"ל Chazal understand that you put a קומץ Kometz worth
of לבונה Levonah. on it. Now, then it says that how do
you offer it up? It says על כל לבונתה יקטיר המזבחה. Al
kol levonatah yaktir hamizbe’acha. You offer it with all of the לבונה.
Levonah. So the simple sense of the פסוק Pasuk seems to be
you have to offer all of the לבונה. Levonah Surprisingly, there is
one position, we assume that that’s רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir that says
if you’re missing any of the לבונה Levonah, it’s invalid. רבי מאיר
קסתם משנה היא רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir k’stam mishna hi Rabbi Meir.
That’s our משנה. Mishna. But we’re going to see that there are
going to be opinions that say that even if you just offer
up one little speck or whatever you call a קורט, Koret, one
little, what do you call
like a pepper, what do you call that, a peppercorn? Whatever, anyway,
a קורט, Koret, whatever you call of לבונה, Levonah then
it it’s we have to actually get some frankincense and see what
it smells like, see what. Yeah. I don’t know, I see sometimes
these aromatic spices at the
supermarket, they’re like these pods.
Anyway, okay. Anyway, if you offer up one little. We’re going to
see a couple of opinions that you have to have all of
the לבונה Levonah there when you actually begin, but when you end
and you actually burn it, it’s enough to have just one or
two little seeds. Okay, very strange. The פסוק Pasuk says על כל
לבונתה. Al kol levonatah. But we’re going to see that. All right?
But everybody agrees you need all the לבונה Levonah there when you
begin. The question is what do you actually have to offer up?
So let’s take a look now at this. חסר לבונה. Chisar levonah.
If any of it is lacking, it’s not good. תנו רבנן. Tanu
rabbanan. We taught. חסרה, Chasra,
the לבונה Levonah was lacking, ועמדה על קורט אחד, Ve’amdah al koret
echad, and all you’re left with is one pod or seed, whatever,
פסולה, Psulah, that’s invalid. One is not enough. או שני קורטין, O
shney kortin, two seeds, כשרה, Kishera, that’s good. דברי רבי יהודה. Divrey
Rabbi Yehuda. That’s what רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda says.
Why would he say that?
We’re going to see in a minute. We’re going to learn it
from the פסוקים. Pesukim. רבי שמעון אומר, Rabbi Shimon omer, רבי שמעון
Rabbi Shimon says, על קורט אחד כשרה. Al koret echad kishera. No,
one seed is enough. פחות מכאן, Pachus mikan, less than that like
half a seed, פסולה Psulah is invalid. והתניא, Vehatanya,
and we taught in a ברייתא, Brayta, but didn’t we teach in
a ברייתא Brayta so now there’s a question if רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon said this or we just assume it’s רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon.
קומץ ולבונה שחסר כל שהוא פסול, Kometz velevonah shechasar kol shehu pasul,
that if the קומץ Kometz is missing anything it’s invalid, that we
know, but it says if the לבונה Levonah, is missing anything it’s
invalid. And we’re for some reason assuming that that’s רבי שמעון. Rabbi
Shimon. And רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon just got through telling us that
even one seed was enough. So תני קורט לבונה שחיסר כל שהוא
פסול. Tani koret levonah shechisar kol shehu pasul.
It doesn’t mean that you’re missing anything from the entire amount of
the לבונה, Levonah. you’re missing something from one the remaining seed of
the לבונה. Levonah You have less than a full seed. Okay, that’s
a pretty hard read, but we will see in a minute anyway
that this is a different opinion. There is an opinion of רבי
מאיר Rabbi Meir that says the entire לבונה Levonah has to be
there when it’s offered up. ואיבעית אימא, Ve’ibayit eima, and if you
want you can say.
Really בזיכין, Bazichin, right? on the left.
Yeah, we’re going to get to
the בזיכין. Bazichin. כאן בלבונה הבאה עם המנחה כאן בלבונה הבאה בפני
עצמה. Kan balevonah haba im hamincha כאן בלבונה הבאה בפני עצמה Kan
balevonah haba bifney atzmah. The לבונה levonah, that comes with the מנחה.
mincha. Oh you have some frankincense
there.
What does it look like? looks like little rocks.
That’s cool.
Or maybe it’s a blossom.
No, it looks like just are those seeds? What is it? It’s
some
kind of... You want to
see?
This is like the basic amount that you would see in a...
oh well the גמרא Gemara says it's not in the תורה. The
גמרא Gemara says though that we learn it out from the קומץ
kometz that it's a קומץ kometz worth. Okay, so and that you
spread, what you basically do is, you mix the מנחה, mincha. you
spread, it's actually quite bizarre what you have to do, because you
take the לבונה, levonah you spread it as a like a top
layer, like the icing on the מנחה. mincha But then when you
come to do the קומץ kometz of the מנחה, mincha. you have
to move it out of the way, right? Because you gotta take
a קומץ kometz without getting any לבונה levonah, in it. So I
would imagine that it's sticky and it's hard to do. And then
לכתחילה, lechatchila, and according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, you have to
do all of the לבונה, levonah which is the simple, even בדיעבד,
bedieved, simple sense of the פסוק, pasuk, you've got to now that
you've got it spread out, you've got to get it all back
into one clump. It's very strange, right, how you would have to
kind of you know do that, but that's we'll see about that
later. Okay. So hard.
Well, does that work for...
it works for a baked מנחה, mincha, it doesn't work for a
non-baked מנחה. mincha. Even for a baked one, you know stuff gets
into the cracks or whatever. Okay. Anyway, so the גמרא Gemara says
here's another way of explaining why lacking can be not good even
according to רבי שמעון. Rabbi Shimon. Are we talking about the לבונה
levonah. that comes with the מנחה? mincha That's where רבי שמעון Rabbi
Shimon says maybe it's only one or two, you know, one little
pod or seed. But let's say somebody... we're going to learn later
that I can donate straight a לוג of oil. Meaning sort of
like the components of a מנחה, mincha I can also donate straight.
And I can donate a לוג of oil. Not donate, bring as
a קרבן. korban. I can bring as a קרבן, korban, you know,
לבונה. levonah So if I'm bringing it as a קרבן, korban, then
it has to be the full amount. Okay, and anything less would
be invalid. The same way if the מנחה mincha was lacking, it
would be invalid. When did רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon say it could
be lacking? When it's the addition to the מנחה mincha and it
was full when it began and now a little is lacking when
it's being offered up. But when I'm bringing it straight as a
קרבן, korban, then that has different
parameters.
You need more?
What? Not you need more, but it can't be lacking.
Okay, that's what I meant, meaning like whatever, you need a bigger
שיעור shiur or you can't just...
Right. When you say... if somebody says 'I obligate myself to bring
a לבונה levonah קרבן', korban no, no, you start with the same
amount, with a קומץ kometz worth. But then when it actually gets
offered, right, then it has to be the full amount. Correct.
No, but I would have thought maybe it means like you know
for like for instance the לחם הפנים lechem hapanim because that's the
only thing you're putting there is a לבונה levonah because they don't
do a קמיצה, kemitza, right?
We're going to get to לחם הפנים lechem hapanim in a minute.
Okay, so let's... okay, but that might have worked, but then I
don't think they would have said, you know, group them together that
way. Okay, so let's take a look. So now we have introduced
the idea of קומץ... kometz of
לבונה levonah as a separate קרבן korban that you need the full
amount. We're going to put that aside and now we're going to
add... now we're going to see the list of different opinions by
how much has to be there. אמר רבי יצחק בר רבי יוסי
אמר רבי יוחנן. Amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Rabbi Yosei amar Rabbi Yochanan.
So here, very nice, the גמרא Gemara organizes all the material for
us. ג' מחלוקות בדבר, Gimmel machlokos badavar, so three-way debate. רבי מאיר
סבר קומץ בתחלה
וקומץ בסוף. Rabbi Meir savar kometz betchila vekometz besof. You need the
full קומץ kometz worth of לבונה levonah at the beginning, everybody says
that, and you need it at the end. When it's offered up,
you need to offer up the full amount. Okay, that would be
our משנה. mishna. That's why it's identified with רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir,
because our משנה mishna says if anything is lacking, presumably at any
time, it's invalid. אמר רבי יהודה סבר קומץ בתחלה ושני קרצין בסוף.
Amar Rabbi Yehuda savar kometz betchila ushnei kartzin besof. You need a
קומץ kometz at the beginning but only two seeds at the end.
That's the ברייתא braisa רבי יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. רבי שמעון סבר קומץ
בתחלה וקורץ אחד בסוף. Rabbi Shimon savar kometz betchila vekoretz echad besof.
The קומץ kometz worth at the beginning and even one little seed
at the end. That's also the opinion in the ברייתא braisa we
quoted.
See where the גמרא Gemara does it, they say פשיטא. pshita.
Right, well. ושלשתן מקרא אחד דרשו. Ushloshtan mikra echad darshu. And they
all got it from one פסוק. pasuk. So here we're going to
see. ואת כל הלבונה אשר על המנחה Ve'es kol halevonah asher al
hamincha and you should offer up all of the לבונה levonah that's
on the מנחה. mincha That sounds pretty clear like רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. So רבי מאיר סבר עד דאית לה ללבונה דאיקבע בהדי מנחה.
Rabbi Meir savar ad d'is lah lalevonah d'ikva bahadi mincha. It says
all of the לבונה levonah. which is on the מנחה. mincha, So
until you offer up all of the לבונה levonah which was sort
of designated together with the מנחה. mincha? So if we're going to
say, as we'll say later, that you designate a קומץ kometz worth,
that everybody agrees to, so you have to offer that entire קומץ
kometz up. That seems pretty straightforward. רבי... רבי... originally
רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda סבר כל kol ואפילו חד קרי. va'afillu chad
karei, כל kol means any, it doesn't mean all. כל kol can
sometimes mean any. Right. רש"י Rashi says quoting the פסוק pasuk לית
שפחתך כל בבית. leis shiphchascha kol babayis. I don't have anything in
the house. So if it means any, ואת כל הלבונה ve'es kol
halevonah means any part of the לבונה. levonah
Which okay, interesting. Now maybe one of the things that pushes this
read is again the idea of how impossible it is to recover
the entire
קומץ kometz once it's been on the surface of the מנחה. mincha
But it is... that's how they're reading. כל means any amount. ואפילו
חד קרי, even one seed. את לרבות קורץ אחר. Es lerabos karetz
acher. It says את כל, es kol, so את es is a
little bit of an extending and adding. So now we have two
seeds. רבי שמעון את לא דריש. Rabbi Shimon et lo darish. רבי
שמעון Rabbi Shimon is not impressed with the את, et, he doesn't
use that to tell anything, so he says even one seed. Okay,
so that is the...
see even like
a...
That's a good question. I don't know. I don't know what to
say. Any whole unit at least it has to be. All right,
ואמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן. Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar
Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan. So now the same רבי יצחק בר יוסף
Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef says in the name of רבי יוחנן: Rabbi
Yochanan: מחלוקת בלבונה הבאה עם מנחה. Machlokes be-levonah ha-ba'ah im mincha. This
sort to clarify the point we made above. They're debating the קומץ
kometz, that comes with the מנחה mincha because you have this פסוק,
passuk, את כל הלבונה, et kol ha-levonah, which might mean any amount.
אבל בלבונה הבאה בפני עצמן, Aval be-levonah ha-ba'ah bifnei atzman, somebody dedicates
frankincense directly where you bring a handbreadth, which חז"ל Chazal learn now,
דברי הכל קומץ בתחילה וקומץ בסוף. deevi ha-kol kometz be-tchilah ve-kometz be-sof.
You need a handbreadth at the beginning and you need to offer
it up. להכי אצטריך אשר על המנחה, La-hachi itztarich asher al ha-mincha,
that's why the תורה says all of the לבונה levonah, or any
of the לבונה levonah, that's on the מנחה. mincha. דבהדי מנחה אין,
De-bahadei mincha in, that when it's with the מנחה, mincha that's when
according to רבי יהודה and רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon it means any,
even one or two pods, but בפני עצמה לא, bifnei atzmah lo,
when it comes by itself, you don't have a special פסוק, passuk,
so therefore if you sanctify the קומץ, kometz, you have to bring
the entire amount.
But how does that work? If I just donate לבונה, levonah. then
what, you don't do a קמיצה, kemitzah, do you? Or you...
No, you take the whole thing and you burn it.
So you just put it in the כלי klee and that's the
whole thing? No קמיצה, kemitzah, you just go on the... Yeah, exactly,
you just go on the מזבח. mizbeach.
Right. And if it's any less than the קומץ, kometz it's not
good. Exactly. Okay, ואמר רבי יצחק, ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak, yes, as the
there isn't really a unit of קטורת, ketores, there aren't grains, it's
a resin, it's kind of like the maple syrup of the Middle
East. It's only once it's extruded from the tree and then dries,
I guess.
Oh, that's interesting.
You're getting this now from your Wikipedia. Where do they get it
from?
Some kind of tree. There are four types of the tree.
Aha.
Interesting. So your point is is that this כורת koret is not
a natural כורת. koret. It's a, so why should it define a
unit? Yeah. It's interesting.
That could be a volume.
Yeah, although it does harden, as you can see in that picture.
Right.
I mean, we do sometimes have that man-made things are defined as
units, like we have an idea of like whole bread and a
half a loaf of bread for like for
שתי הלחם shtei ha-lechem or whatever for Shabbos or other things, some
preference for a whole loaf, even though that's man-made as well.
But it is a good point, like what does it define a
כורת? koret?
Right, that it crystallizes once
it hardens, it's a unit. Right, that's the point, right, exactly. Interesting.
Okay.
So now the גמרא says, again to qualify the other case of
לבונה, levonah like Michael thought, which is what comes with the tree,
what comes with the tree? What comes with the לחם הפנים. lechem
ha-panim. ואמר רבי יצחק בר יוסף אמר רבי יוחנן מחלוקת בלבונה הבאה
עם מנחה. Ve-amar Rabbi Yitzchak bar Yosef amar Rabbi Yochanan machlokes be-levonah
ha-ba'ah im mincha. Again, this is a debate when it comes with
a מנחה. mincha. אבל בלבונה הבאה בבזיכין, Aval be-levonah ha-ba'ah be-vazichin,
when it comes in the like the cups or whatever they are,
the vessel, spoons, that were with the לחם הפנים, lechem ha-panim, דברי
הכל שני קמצין
בתחילה ושני קמצין בסוף. deevi ha-kol shnei kmatzin be-tchilah ve-shnei kmatzin be-sof.
Wait, each one of them or... I'm going to say. We have
not discussed yet how much there was, but חז"ל Chazal understand again
the קומץ kometz being the שיעור shiur for לבונה. levonah So if
you have these two vessels that were on the שולחן shulchan that
had לבונה levonah, in them, then they understand that each one had
a קומץ kometz, worth, which is bigger than I think we would
have imagined. I don't know, I would have imagined because sometimes when
you see pictures of the שולחן, shulchan, they look like these tiny
little tablespoons on it, but actually if it has to hold a
קומץ, kometz. that's a non-trivial amount or whatever. Anyway, so you have
these little things that are each one is holding a קומץ. kometz
So it's a total of two קמצים. kmatzim. So there it has
to start that way and you have to burn it. If you
burn any less than that, it's no good.
No, so but do they mean two כורת koret for each one
of these spoons, or do they mean קמצים?
kmatzim? They have to be full. Each spoon holds a קומץ kometz
and it has to start that way and it has to be
burned in its entirety. Okay.
No, but if it has more and and you only end up
as one קומץ kometz? and you're still fine, right, for each one
of them?
You mean if they were overflowing? I'm not sure more would be
fine.
Each one had exactly a קומץ? kometz Yes. Oh, they didn't have
more than that just in case?
No, presumably not. I mean, that's what it's saying. Okay. So I
mean, same like the מנחה mincha had exactly a קומץ kometz. and
according to רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir had to offer the whole thing
up. Okay. So the גמרא says, דברי הכל שני קמצין בתחילה, deevi
ha-kol shnei kmatzin be-tchilah, you have to start with two קמצים kmatzim
ושני קמצין בסוף. ve-shnei kmatzin be-sof. פשיטא Pshita obviously, I guess because
since there's no פסוק passuk to say even a small amount. So
whenever there's not a פסוק, passuk, then we assume it has to
be the full amount. No, מהו דתימא כיון דבהדי לחם אתיא, mahu
de-teima keivan de-bahadei lechem atyah,
since it's coming with the bread, כאשר על המנחה דמיא, ka'asher al
ha-mincha damya, it fits in the פסוק passuk that says on the
מנחה mincha because the bread is the bread, it's like the מנחה
mincha and this is with the bread. So maybe it does fit
in that פסוק passuk and we would allow one or two seeds
or whatever, קמשמע לן kamashma lan that no, it's separate. Now, I
want to say the logic here. So far we're dealing with פסוקים,
psukim, but the logic is that the מנחה you always offer up
the קומץ. kometz And the קומץ kometz is the primary thing you
offer up. It's actually מנחה is an interesting phenomenon because you don't
have a parallel to the idea of the קטורת ketores by any
other קרבן. korban. But every other thing you have the blood that's
offered end of story. You do have חלב, chelev, but חלב chelev
is not part of what makes it kosher. But here you have
the קומץ kometz. which is the primary plus the לבונה levona and
if you don't do the לבונה, levona. then it's not going to...
to be kosher. So it's a second thing, it's completely physically different,
it's somewhat secondary, but it's necessary to make it כשר. kosher. Which
by the way, as you can imagine, the גמרא is going to
have fun with this with פיגול pigul and מפגלין בחצי מתיר mefaglin
bechatzi matir when you have a פיגול pigul for one and not
with the other. Okay, but anyway, we can worry about that later.
So that's where you could say well maybe even a little bit
of לבונה levona because you basically did the קומץ. kometz But the
other cases where you need the full amount are cases where all
you have is the לבונה. levona I sanctified the לבונה levona. as
a full קרבן, korban, that's all I have, have to burn it
all up. The לבונה levona from the table, it's true that there's
bread and it's על המנחה, al hamincha, but there's no קומץ kometz
from the bread. All you have is the לבונה. levona So in
those cases, if it's the primary thing that's offered, you need the
full amount. That seems to be the logic. All right, so let's
just finish up to the משנה mishna here. Let's see. So the
גמרא says פשיטא מהו דתימא. peshita mahu deteima. Okay, we just did
that. פליגי בה רב אמי ורב יצחק נפחא. pligi bah Rav Ami
veRav Yitzchak Napcha.
So actually this was a debate of רב אמי Rav Ami and
רב יצחק נפחא. Rav Yitzchak Napcha. חד אמר מחלוקת בלבונה הבאה עם
מנחה אבל בלבונה הבאה בפני עצמה דברי הכל קומץ בתחילה וקומץ בסוף,
chad amar machlokes belevona habaa im mincha aval belevona habaa bifnei atzma
divrei hakol kometz betchila vekometz besof,
like we said before. The debate of a small amount was only
when it came with the מנחה, but by itself everybody agrees you
need the full amount, the קומץ kometz even at the end. וחד
אמר כמחלוקת בזו כך מחלוקת בזו, vechad amar kemachlokes bezo kach machlokes
bezo, and here there's a contrary voice that says no, even when
it's coming by itself there are those that say that even רבי
יהודה ורבי שמעון Rabbi Yehuda veRabbi Shimon that even a tiny amount
is enough.
And this משנה, mishna, חסר לבונה פסולה, chasar levona pesula, if the
לבונה levona was lacking it's invalid, and we just discussed how much
lacking is lacking. But now the גמרא discusses what happens to too
much. היתיר כשרה. hayatir kesheira. Does that suggest, because it didn't say
too much, everywhere else it said too much is also a problem.
So does this suggest that too much לבונה levona. is כשר? kosher?
והתניא יתיר פסולה, vehatanya yatir pesula,
if it's too much it's invalid.
They didn't say how much is enough.
Well, we've been assuming a קומץ kometz all along.
No, it's not in the משנה.
mishna. All right, that's true. אמר רמי בר חמא כגון שהפריש לה
שני קמצים. Amar Rami bar Chama kegon shehifrish lah shenei kematzim. What
happens is that you designated two קמצים. kematzim. So what does that
mean? So
that would be a case of where it would be too much,
where ריבוי ribui would be not good. So the question is, that's
very lovely, but what's the answer to why it's not in our
משנה? mishna? So let's take a look. ואמר רמי בר חמא הפריש
שני קמצים ואבד אחד מהן. veamar Rami bar Chama hifrish shenei kematzim
veavad echad mehen.
So if you designated two קמצים kematzim worth of לבונה levona. and
one was lost. קודם קמיצה, kodem kemitza, if it was lost before
you did the קמיצה, kemitza, so then לא הוקבע, lo hukba,
then it's not like meaning what happened? When does the קומץ kometz
get defined to be connected to the מנחה? You could say maybe
from the moment you lay it down. But maybe not, what if
I laid down on the thing two קמצים kematzim and I realized
I put too much and I took one of them off. Is
it still כשר? kosher? So what he's going to say is it's
defined as being too much from the act, from the moment you
do the קמיצה. kemitza. That defines it as this is the מנחה
you have when you've done the מנחה and then if it's too
much you've got a problem. So if you have two קמצים, kematzim,
ואבד אחד מהן קודם קמיצה, veavad echad mehen kodem kemitza,
now what he actually sounds like is you didn't even mix them
in, they're just standing separate to be added to the מנחה. Okay,
when are they defined with the מנחה as a problem and when
are they not? So if one of them was lost before you
did the קמיצה, kemitza, so then לא הוקבע, lo hukba, it's not
designated to be with the מנחה. The מנחה now only has one
קומץ kometz left and you're fine. אחר קמיצה, achar kemitza, first you
did the קמיצה kemitza after having designated or sanctified two units of
לבונה. levona So then when you did the קמיצה kemitza you had
too much לבונה. levona, Then הוקבעו, hukbe-u, they were connected, established with
the מנחה and it's invalid because you have too much.
Wait, so we're talking about the second process, right, where you already,
because you start out with the flour and the oil and then
the לבונה all in, then you do the קמיצה, kemitza, then you
put it in a קידוש כלי. kiddush kli. We're talking about that
part,
right, where you have instead of one קומץ worth you have two
קמצים kematzim worth.
But what about from the very beginning when you bring your מנחה
and you have to have לבונה, how much do you need?
One more time, I didn't get. Let me finish and then you'll
ask the question because it's basically almost 8:30 and I just want
to finish. Okay, so the גמרא is saying that the משנה mishna
suggests that too much is כשר, kosher, isn't too much פסול? So
the גמרא says there are times where you could have too much
and it could still be כשר. kosher. What is that? You designated
too much, but the extra got lost or destroyed or removed before
you did the קמיצה. kemitza. Then it would be okay. It's the
moment of קמיצה kemitza that matters. And let's just finish this up.
אמר רמי בר חמא הפריש ארבעה קמצים לשני בזיכין. Amar Rami bar
Chama hifrish arba-ah kematzim lishnei beizichin. So for the two בזיכין, beizichin,
instead of having two קמצים, kematzim, one each, right, for the לחם
הפנים, lechem hapanim, you had four. ואבדו שנים מהם, veavdu shenayim mehem,
and two were lost. So now you're back to the right amount.
So it depends whether they were lost early enough. If they were
lost קודם סילוק בזיכין kodem ssiluk beizichin before you removed the בזיכין,
beizichin, which is like the taking of the קמיצה, kemitza, the designating
of what defines the unit, לא הוקבעו, lo hukbe-u, they have not
been connected to it, established. לאחר סילוק בזיכין L’achar siluk bazichin
but if all four were around until you removed the בזיכין bazichin
then at that moment you had too much and it's a problem.
הוקבעו Hukbe'u they were established with it. הא תו למה לי Ha
tu lama li why do I need the second case of the
שולחן shulchan isn't it essentially the same? So היינו הך hainu hach
it's the same. No. מהו דתימא Ma'u detema I might have thought
כיון דבריר קומץ דידיה kevan de-barir kometz didey
this is an idea we said before since the what you're going
to remove is designated it's already in those cups כיון שהגיע זמנה
לפרקה כמאן דפרקה דמיא. kevan she-higi zmana le-farka keman de-farka damya.
When the time to remove it comes it's like you've already removed
it. So it's not the act of removing that designates but as
soon as the time comes it's like it's been removed right? We
had that idea before. קא משמע לן no it's the act of
removing. So the only reason I would have thought it was different
is maybe here you don't even need to remove it to designate
maybe the time is enough. But in the end what we're saying
is that too much why did the משנה mishna not say it's
פסול? Because sometimes it's כשרה kashera if it got lacking before. Now
since he talks about designated and not placing on and talks about
getting lost it sounds like it's not mixed up and therefore if
you lose it it can still be כשרה kashera if it got
destroyed or lost early enough. What if you actually put it on
top of it right? There maybe you can't reverse. Maybe once it's
physically on top even if then you removed some before the taking
of the קמיצה kemitzah it might still remain invalid. But at least
his scenario is it's been designated not on top and you can
fix it before the קמיצה. kemitzah. Okay we will end here.